Uh hello, my name is Ivan Malikov and
I'm recording from Ramenska.
I thought nice idea to show big YouTube
audience uh Soviet playground.
We go.
[Music]
In the 20th century, the Soviet Union
and the United States developed
different playground ideologies.
While both saw them as vital for
children's development, their approaches
were different. One valued
standardization, utilitarian play, the
other more varied and safe. After the
1917 revolution, the new Soviet regime
viewed playgrounds as tools for
political education. They were training
grounds intended to build a strong
Soviet child. This this is the most
important element of playgrounds.
horizontal bar for pull-up and kind of
you know um pushup.
In uh 1930
government want to create new men big
idea communism you know they make a new
rule
get
ready for labor and defense. The first
pull-up bars appeared in schoolyards in
the 30s. They were training equipment
for kids to get a minimum number of
pull-ups required to get a GTO badge.
One of these badges was a market
prestige and often an entrance
requirement or booster for higher
institutions.
Hundreds of millions of these badges
were issued. But -40° C winters and
heavy loads meant the training equipment
needed to be strong, easy to use, and
ubiquitous. Early plastics were too
brittle. Steel tubing was cheap. A small
neighborhood crew only needed to know
how to weld scrap metal to be able to
make kids have an opportunity to play
and practice. Everyone was ready for a
big war with Germany.
Yeah. Fight in the army maybe or uh you
know make work in gulag support the
country this way.
People in the past were tough, you know,
like uh big nail you put in the railway.
Uh how you call it?
Oh, these things um
these things scare me always.
Look at this.
Yeah,
look at that.
Oh, here's another one. Look. Uh, big
Soviet cartoon. Very famous.
Chibarashka.
But why? Some say the moon. Why choose
this as our goal? And they may well ask,
why climb the highest mountain? During
the 60s, the space race reached its
peak. In line with its previous pursuit
of making stronger children, the Soviets
began building space themed playgrounds
to encourage cosmic achievement at the
height of the Cold War. We choose to go
to the moon. We choose to go to the
moon. The US also had spacethemed
playground equipment, but the eastern
block had a design coordination. The
West did not.
Guided by an iron fist, children were a
key target of the propaganda drive.
Mass-produced and standardized in
factories, space playgrounds rippled
across the country. Famous cosminauts
and scientists were pushed as role
models and Soviet urban planners and
designers increasingly incorporated
space motifs into playground equipment.
Yuri Gagarian was a very important man,
very famous like Elvis Presley in uh in
America.
[Music]
So USSR build a build a lot of this uh
you know space space playground thing.
Okay. So children grow like Gagarian and
go to space.
After the war, the USSR had millions of
bombed out families and nowhere near
enough homes. So Nikita Kruev, the
Soviet leader from 1953 to 1964, slashed
building costs and ordered that all new
housing be made from pre-fabricated
reinforced concrete panels which could
be rolled from factory to site. The
slabs were made into blocks, which then
became bigger planning units. They had
their own schools and of course
playgrounds. Soviet building codes
required a minimum outdoor play space
per child. So in these huge estates, the
shared courtyards became giant
playfields. Here's an example.
In Russian, you say
I was uh I was in the corner and I could
not go anywhere and the guy want to tag
me. So I jump on the other side of
Vlazilka on this long bar and hit my
face.
I feel a metal taste in mouth. I think
it was rust from the bar. But it is
actually blood because you know the
tooth come out. So you know 40 years no
maintenance
and still get your tooth out.
Yeah, Malia.
[Music]
Kids must be playing where
very ugly.
[Music]
Although they were standardized, Soviet
playgrounds could still be unique in
their use of unconventional sculptures.
True uniformity really only existed on
paper. Locals would add their own
personality using dead tree stumps or
leftover rebar. Soviet playgrounds could
come with their own handmade metal
animal figures, strange wood carved
creatures, and folktale characters.
Notably absent in many Soviet
playgrounds, though, were complex
composite structures. These are
multi-element play rigs built from
several modules bolted together into one
big unit. Slides and swings tend to stay
alone in play areas. And if a large
multi-element playground equipment did
exist, it would be strange. He could do
a loop on this thing and I cannot yet.
We uh play game who can jump most far
away from swing. So he make the loop
first before jump to show how cool he
is. Yeah, that he can do loop.
So he fly uh really high after the jump,
land safe. Okay. But too close to the
swing and swing goes uh
does uh um swing. Yeah. And it goes
right in his head. Banging bang.
Yeah. Sound like a big big broken tuning
fork.
cousin have scar on his head still from
this. That's the most gaggarian he ever
was.
I show you last one. Okay, last thing on
this playground.
This last one I explain.
dead
[Applause]
yet.
kids. Uh, no, no, no, no.
Good drawing. Uh, in staircase.
What is this? One day there was a
anarchy.
uh gods ruled the earth
each of them of one application for a
specific task. They abused
humanity and uh fight each other.
Civilization went to slumber
and new gods appear and depose previous
but anarchy remained.
But uh then something new happened.
A god appeared that create a uh unified
platform
for everything.
His name was Udu.
He unite all the application in one hole
that would service all the needs of the
business. But he had one last trick.
He started with offering free
application
that can compete with each of the of the
app gods.
Such he became the king of the kingdom.
rule your kingdom where Udu give you
power not only over your business but
also gives you free application with
unlimited hosting and report.
Let's do it.
[Music]
[Applause]
Keep recording. Okay. Uh, keep
recording.
[Applause]
Uh,
not good. Um, where's my head?
[Applause]
America.
[Music]
America followed a different trajectory,
mainly shaped by consumer culture and
safety.
While Soviet yards may have been made of
packed dirt, the US relied on wood
fiber, poured in rubber, and
well-manicured grass.
Grass cut well.
Must cut every day.
only grass.
Um
I hear Americans use uh
uh blower for leaves
uh and uh dry car after wash with this.
Is this true?
Use a blower to blow dog off the
grass.
I get it.
You can eat from this grass, you know.
It's so clean.
Originally, American playgrounds were
also made of metal and hard materials.
But by the late 20th century, the US
underwent a playground safety
revolution.
They were not just meant to keep kids
busy and off dangerous streets. They
were meant to inculcate fair play, good
manners and healthy habits. They became
familycentric and community organized
recreation. American playgrounds were
destinations for family outings. A
parent or babysitter would take children
to the park for an hour of play.
But the American playground diverged in
a unique way. Adult supervision was a
norm rather than exception. But it was
not just out of concern for the child's
safety. Liability and litigation
concerns made adult supervision even
more necessary out of concern for
financial damages.
I was uh in chat roulette, you know, a
video chat with random uh people from
the internet.
Connect me to American guy my age.
Tell me um
about American playground. Strange
strange things.
He said cannot run on playground.
Kid fall heard um uh something and
parents
uh make legal attack on school and
school in big trouble and lose a lot of
money and uh maybe how $100,000
maybe even more.
So school uh make new rules. No running
on playground. No run, no fight.
Um only shooting still. Okay. I think
uh kid can't pick up stick
because you can use stick as a sword and
hit someone.
Of course you use stick as sword. What
else stick for?
Must be someone here.
[Applause]
Hello.
[Music]
In contrast to Soviet playgrounds,
American playgrounds do commonly feature
multi-purpose play structures which
combine slides, bridges, and climbing
into one unit. As the playgrounds began
to standardize due to the growth of
suburbia, manufacturers softened their
materials and relied more on coated
metal and most important of all plastic.
Okay,
now this is playground I talk about.
Impressive.
Yeah.
Not even slide is hard
plastic
always safe for child.
This American friend uh tell me every
playground have um
uh
committee
of uh suburban mother with uh too much
time.
They always watch.
No chance to hide. American play areas
often also included benches, picnic
tables, or trash cans. They also came
with posted rules and warning signs,
indicating that it wasn't just a space
designed for kids, but also adults.
Playground rules.
Adult supervision required.
No running on playground.
[Applause]
What do you think kid is? The kid must
run.
Use equipment properly.
[Applause]
Stand in straight line to use swing one
by one. Everyone is safe.
Oh.
Hello.
[Applause]
Wave back is polite. America
is free country. People with big dreams,
freedom to do everything. Uh
you see um no homeless man
sleeping here under this roof. No
graffiti. Even
[Applause]
if graffiti, my friend said uh entire
police
uh called to investigate who did it.
Even if some kid just uh play around,
you know,
I never see a playground like this.
Yeah, maybe I criticize very much. It's
a beautiful playground.
Very good. Looks very good.
Maybe looks good because equipment used
properly.
Americans are good people.
[Applause]
Uh, what is this?
Police get down. Get down on the ground.
Okay. Okay. Okay. Okay. Put the gun
down. No. No. No. Oh, no. It's just a
camera.